Alright, בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is נ"ו, nun vav,
and we pick
up five lines from the top, דם היוצא, dam ha-yotzei, end of
the line, דם היוצא. dam ha-yotzei. Basically, we're going on the משנה
mishnah that discusses various things that, particularly things that come from people's
bodies but not limited to that, that are טמא tamei and whether
they're only when they're moist or even when they're
dried. And we're now discussing the various fluids of a זב zav
and we mentioned the תורה Torah speaks about spit. We included, in
addition to spit, by an extra word in the פסוק, pasuk, we
included also like phlegm in the discussion about mucus of the nose.
And we also included, based on that, that was compared to spit,
and then compared to the actual זיבה, ziva, the flow from the
penis,
we also included urine. But we excluded other things that come from
the... thank you so much... like blood. If blood were to
come from the penis, it would not be a problem. And now
we're going to try to understand how we know this and what
the difference between which fluids of a זב zav are an אב
טומאה av tumah and which are not. So it says like this:
five lines again from the top, נ"ו עמוד א', nun vav amud
aleph, end of the line. דם היוצא מפי האמה מנלן דטהור? Dam
ha-yotzei mi-pi ha-amah minalan de-tahor? How do you know that when blood
comes from the penis, how do you know that that is טהור?
tahor? Meaning,
we know that the flow is explicit in the תורה. Torah. We've
included by a verse that something else that comes from there, i.e.,
urine is טמא, tamei, but how do you know that the blood
is טהור? tahor? So דתניא, de-tanya, we taught in the ברייתא, baraita,
יכול יהא דם היוצא מפיו ומפי האמה טמא? Yakhol yehei dam ha-yotzei
mi-piv u-mi-pi ha-amah tamei? Maybe blood that comes from a person's mouth—meaning
we have basically places where fluids come from from a זב, zav,
they're טמא: tamei: the mouth, which is spit and phlegm, and as
we discussed also like mucus. And then we also
have the genitals where if it comes from there, the flow and
urine, the flow of the זיבה, ziva, that's also טמא. tamei. But
how do you know if blood comes from either of those two
locations, how do you know it's
טהור? tahor? Maybe they should be טמא tamei when blood comes from
those locations. תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, the verse teaches, זובו טמא הוא,
zovo tamei hu, his flow it is טמא. tamei. הוא טמא, Hu
tamei, only it, the flow is
טמא, tamei, ואין דם היוצא מפיו ומפי האמה טמא אלא טהור, ve-ein
dam ha-yotzei mi-piv u-mi-pi ha-amah tamei ella tahor, אלא טהור, ella tahor,
טהור. tahor. Okay, so we have a verse that says הוא hu
which is limiting, but we have other verses which are inclusive. So
basically what we've done is we've taken the fact that the תורה
Torah says the flow is טמא tamei and included urine, the fact
that the תורה Torah says the spit is טמא tamei and included
phlegm
and mucus.
And then,
but what we've excluded from both of those sources is blood based
on a verse of הוא. hu. So now the גמרא's Gemara going
to ask the obvious question: how do you know when what you're
going to include—phlegm, mucus, and urine—and exclude blood? And you're also excluding
sweat. Well, right, other things as well. So the גמרא, Gemara, although
that's not from the same location. What?
What are you excluding?
Sweat. But that's not from the same location. Here we're focusing particularly
on the mouth and the genitals, which are the areas where the
תורה Torah is explicit that certain fluids are טמא. tamei. So the
גמרא Gemara says, ואיפוך אנא? Ve-eippukh ana? Why not reverse it? Why
not say the blood is טמא tamei and these things are טהור?
tahor? So אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בן יוחי, Amar Rabbi
Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai, and this is what we were
mentioning yesterday, which we've known from their places, the way the גמרא
Gemara conceptualizes the concept of spit: דומיא דרוק, dumya de-rok, similar to
spit which the תורה Torah explicit that the spit is
טמא. tamei. מה רוק שמתעגל ויוצא, Mah rok she-mit'agel ve-yotzei, spit collects
first before it comes out. אף כל שמתעגל ויוצא, Af kol she-mit'agel
ve-yotzei, anything that collects before it comes out. יצא דם, Yatza dam,
which excludes blood, שאין מתעגל ויוצא, she-ein mit'agel ve-yotzei, it doesn't collect.
If you got, if you cut yourself on your skin, or if
you have some reason that you're bleeding inside of your body, then
it's not
gathering and collecting and coming out the same way, of course the
body is made in a way that the spit collects in your
mouth before it comes out, or phlegm collects and then comes out,
or urine collects and then comes out. So that is the conceptual
category. So yes, the תורה Torah explicit about the flow, the זיבה
ziva that makes him a זב, zav, and the spit, and we
conceptualize it as things that collect before coming out, and that's how
we know that if we're going to exclude something, we're going to
exclude blood, which does not fit into that category. And now the
גמרא Gemara asks one minute, the question that we ourselves raised yesterday.
So the גמרא Gemara says, יצא דם שאין מתעגל ויוצא, Yatza dam
she-ein mit'agel ve-yotzei, so it excludes blood that is not like that.
והרי חלב שבאשה, Ve-harei chalav she-be-ishah, how about a woman's milk, mother's
milk, שמתעגל ויוצא, she-mit'agel ve-yotzei, that that collects and then it comes
out. ואמר מר, Ve-amar mar, we said yesterday that that is not
considered a מעיין, ma'ayan, that is not, if a woman is a
זבה, zavah, it is not an אב טומאה, av tumah, it is
not a source of טומאה. tumah. ואמר מר, Ve-amar mar, we said
yesterday, חלב שבאשה מטמא טומאת משקין, chalav she-be-ishah metamei tumat mashkin, if
a woman's milk, mother's milk, if she is a זבה, zavah, then
that is טמא tamei because it receives טומאה tumah from her, it's
טמא tamei as a liquid.
So טומאת משקין tumat mashkin אין, in, yes, טמא tamei as a
liquid that conducted טומאה, tumah, אבל לא טומאה חמורה, aval lo tumah
chamurah, but it is not considered one of the primary fluids of
a זב zav and a זבה zavah to be considered an אב
הטומאה. av hatumah. It's not in the same category as spit. So
how come you include, so the Torah's explicit about spit.
Spit, that's a source of טומאה tumah by a זב. zav. Based
on spit we abstract that's מתעגל ויוצא mit'agel veyotzei and we have
extra פסוקים pesukim that lead to greater, to help us to broaden
the category, so we wind up including things like phlegm and mucus
and possibly mucus and urine. But and we exclude blood. But why
are we also going to then exclude milk? Milk should be in
that category.
אלא אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בן יוחי. Ella amar Rabbi
Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai. Rabbi Yochanan says in the name
of Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai, דומיא דרוק, dumya derok, it is similar
to spit, but more than just the one criteria we mentioned. מה
רוק, Ma rok, here's, here's the two important criteria of spit. Number
one, מה רוק מתעגל ויוצא, ma rok mit'agel veyotzei, first collects before
coming out of the body. And number two, וחוזר ונבלע, vechozer venivla,
it can be swallowed back, right? You can swallow back your spit,
it doesn't have to come out, it's collecting but you can swallow
it back, presumably also your phlegm or whatever. Not urine. Now that's
the problem. So anyway, יצא דם שאינו מתעגל ויוצא, yatza dam she'eino
mit'agel veyotzei, which excludes blood which does not collect, יצא חלב שבאשה
yatza chalav shebe'ishah and also excludes mother's milk שאף על פי שמתעגל
ויוצא, she'af al pi shemit'agel veyotzei, although it collects and comes out,
אינו חוזר ונבלע, eino chozer venivla, it cannot get reabsorbed back into
the body. Of course the problem is that the גמרא Gemara said
this to exclude milk but presumably urine is still included. So since
when is urine that way?
So if you look at תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot says, let's take
a look, or maybe it's רש"י, Rashi, hold on, where's רש"י? Rashi?
אף כל, Af kol, so if you look at רש"י, Rashi, it's
about one, two, three, four, five lines down the narrow line, כגון
סילון
של מי רגלים חוזר ונבלע. kegon silon shel mei raglayim chozer venivla.
So it says like the stream of urine can be reabsorbed. Which
I don't know, you know, again there's some גמרות Gemorot that also
speak about not, you know, about health concerns about sort of interrupting
your urination but I always assumed that those גמרות Gemorot were, and
the way they phrase it is that the stream gets reabsorbed, but
I always assumed that that was more or less metaphorical. But anyway,
you know, because obviously it doesn't get reabsorbed you just stop urinating,
right? I mean it might be abrupt but it's not that somehow
the urine goes back in. So anyway I do not, I have
no way of actually explaining why the גמרא Gemara thinks that urine
is different than milk, that milk somehow it does not get reabsorbed
but urine does.
What about
צחצוחי, tzichtzuchei, right?
צחצוחי, Tzichtzuchei, yeah, but צחצוחי tzichtzuchei actually Dov was asking me that
yesterday, I didn't check it up. צחצוחי Tzichtzuchei is טמא tamei because
it's not as necessarily as a מעיין. ma'ayan. צחצוחי Tzichtzuchei is always
an אב הטומאה. av hatumah. The question is, is it also considered
one of the מעיינות ma'ayanot of a זב? zav? The difference would
be that צחצוחי tzichtzuchei by itself would not be טמא במשא, tamei
bemasa, would not be
טמא לבגדים. tamei levigadim. So I have to check up whether we
consider, now the גמרא Gemara also says that צחצוחי tzichtzuchei of a
זב zav we say אי אפשר בלא צחצוחי זיבה, ee efshar belo
tzichtzuchei zivah, there's going to be drops of זיבה zivah in it.
So I have to check whether we consider צחצוחי tzichtzuchei primarily a
מעיין. ma'ayan. It certainly is not mentioned here as such. But I
really do not understand the difference between milk and blood in that
regard. Milk and urine in that regard. מיטב, Meitav, do they say
anything there that's helpful?
Not yet. Okay, you'll let us know. Anyway, all right, so moving
on. So that's at least that distinction.
I can tell you what it says. It compares to saliva, causes
us to include various types of phlegm, all three fluids are similar
to saliva in that they collect and go out but are reabsorbed
if not expelled. That's what you just said already. All these three
fluids are all similar in this regard, a single inclusionary expression would
not suffice to include all three rather.
All right, it's not basically trying to tell us the difference between
urine and milk. Moving on. All right, so that's interesting but the
גמרא Gemara somehow assumes that that's a difference. Now I should say
that the גמרא Gemara is not,
never gets back discussing the issue about the mucus, right? Because that
conceptually is certainly seems to be in that same category of מתעגל
ויוצא. mit'agel veyotzei. So at the end I think part of the
question here is that how much is it just this abstract category
and then you would include mucus or how much in the end
do you also need the פסוק pasuk to include it and then
there could be a debate whether you have an explicit פסוק pasuk
to include this or not. Anyway that's the basis for making these
lines of distinction about the things that are considered a source of
טומאה tumah for זב zav and things that are not. Yes.
What I mean when blood comes out of anywhere
else it's not a good sign. See a doctor. Yes. Same is
true if you have an unusual flow, a non-semen or non-urine coming
out you know it's also see a doctor, right?
I know but
the... saliva and sweat and all those things, those are things that
you expect your body right, right to secrete. So the distinction would
not be made.
Yeah, the גמרא Gemara is not really interested from the health perspective,
like which is natural and not natural and so on. I mean,
you're true, the גמרא Gemara could say well blood is not natural,
but the point is is that the זיבה, ziva, the whole thing
that makes this person into a זב zav is an unnatural flow,
you know? So the unnatural nature of it, well, it's also okay.
I mean okay, anyway, so unhealthy certainly. So the גמרא, Gemara, you
know, that is true, it's a difference, but that's not one I
think the גמרא Gemara feels is relevant presumably because the זיבה ziva
certainly falls into that category.
So what is the, what is relevant? What...
You know, it's just an abstraction, the fact that the תורה Torah
speaks about certain things and we're trying to understand what are sort
of distinctive about those characteristics. Now you're right, I guess your point
is well as long as you're saying similar to spit, why isn't
say similar to spit that it's a, that it's a natural secretion?
You know, it's a good point, why the תורה Torah does not,
you know, bring that into the discussion. I really don't know.
They can keep that separate for that reason and they can keep
milk separate not because of this,
because it's something only that's relevant to women. So once you have...
Ah, yeah, but again there are טומאות tumot for women, there are
טומאות tumot for the man.
I mean these are all potential lines of distinction. Right. Yeah, you're
right. I mean it is a good question and if the גמרא
Gemara is sort of working backwards, I mean it's, you raise a
good point, which is anytime we want to abstract a category there's
going to be an enormous amount of interpretation in terms of which
are the relevant factors to define as the defining characteristics and which
ones are marginal or trivial. You're absolutely correct. And why we pick
the ones we do and not others, I really don't know.
To give a reason that doesn't apply doesn't seem as compelling.
Well, okay, but let's assume that the גמרא Gemara believes it does
apply. So, but you are right in general that any sort of
saying, oh, here are the defining characteristics is an act of interpretation
because you know you choose what are defining characteristics. Right. That's absolutely
correct. Okay. You know, you could have just said that all this
stuff is not red. You know? So, right, all this stuff is
relatively white or clear.
No, but what I said has some meaning. I know.
It's true. Right.
Something,
you
would not, if you saw blood coming out of...
Yes. It would be a very unusual...
You would have to say, oh, something's not right.
Exactly. Exactly. Alright, let's wrap this up. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this: ונילף מזובו. Venilef mizovo. מה זובו שאין מתעגל ויוצא מטמא
אף כל. Mah zovo she-ein mitagel ve-yotze mitamei af kol.
So why not learn from the flow? Because the actual flow that
makes him a זב, zav, this was sort of what I was
saying back to Rachel, you, maybe you don't want to emphasize as
sort of natural because the flow itself that makes him a זב
zav is not natural. So the גמרא Gemara says, yeah, well why
not learn from flow, that flow doesn't have these characteristics of מתעגל
ויוצא, mitagel ve-yotze, it doesn't collect. So maybe you can't use that
as a defining characteristic because the very flow itself that makes him
into a זב zav does not have that characteristic, doesn't collect before
coming out. Presumably, you know, I think they tend to feel that
the זיבה ziva is something, it's not the same, but you know,
whatever, they something sort of similar to like a venereal disease that
just causes, you know, some flowing coming out that's not controlled. So
the גמרא Gemara says it's not מתעגל ויוצא, mitagel ve-yotze, it doesn't
collect. אף כל. Af kol. אמר רבא: Amar Rava: מזובו ליכא למיילף.
Mizovo leika lemeylaf. No, that's not a relevant example, שכן גורם טומאה
לאחרים. she-kein gorem tumah leachreim.
The זיבה, ziva, the flow itself is what makes him a זב.
zav. So that could have a different parameter. We're trying to talk
about the things not that make the person a זב, zav, but
after the person is a זב, zav, certain types of liquids and
you know,
fluids that are an אב הטומאה av hatumah but not that make
him. And there all the תורה Torah gives us is spit and
we have to abstract from spit. So we're going to focus on
spit as this idea of collecting and coming out. But that by
the way, Rachel, is also, strengthens your point, that once we're saying
that the flow that makes him a זב zav is not relevant,
that's making him a זב, zav, we're talking about the fluids after
he's a זב zav and spit is your example, then natural should
certainly could have been a pretty reasonable criteria that we are for
some reason not using. So that is a very good point. Okay,
so those are the various fluids of a זב. zav. And now
we move on into the next case of the משנה. mishnah. והשרץ.
Ve-hasheretz. A dead rodent that also causes טומאה. tumah. That's explicit in
the תורה. Torah. And here we are, but the משנה mishnah's point
is not to say that it causes טומאה tumah but only when
it's moist, not when it's dried out. אמר ריש לקיש: Amar Reish
Lakish: שרץ שיבש ושלדו קיימת טמא. Sheretz she-yavesh ve-shildo kayemet tamei. Sort
of against the simple sense of the משנה. mishnah. Even if you
have a rodent that has completely desiccated and dried out, if its
form is still present, if it still sort of has the shape
of this rodent, then it causes טומאה, tumah, which interestingly shows you,
you know, there's a conceptual question about why do we think that
when something is dried out it doesn't cause טומאה? tumah? It could
just be גזירת הכתוב gezeirat hakatuv like we learned from various verses
that we haven't even quoted some of the verses, we will in
a minute. But it could also be conceptually that we're saying like
it loses its, there are two ways of defining it. One is
that it's no longer the thing itself. If something is dried out
and desiccated, it's no longer the thing itself. Maybe that's indicated by
the משנה. mishnah. The משנה mishnah says if you resubmerge it in
water. reconstitutes
or not reconstitutes, that sort of means that it's not in its
shape or whatever, some refreshens, I don't know, anyway, then it is
not considered dried out. So maybe it's just it's not the thing
anymore. Or maybe it is the thing, but its significance is undermined
once it's dried out. So the fact that ריש לקיש Resh Lakish
further says well to counterbalance the dried out, if it retained its
shape, that's good enough. It seems to be his point is that
it's a question about has it lost its significance. So as long
as it still has the shape, it's retained its like significance. You
know, it does not seem like if you would say this is
no longer rodent meat here, it's just dirt. So it's dirt in
the shape of a rodent, you know, but it seems that the
idea that the shape matters we're more talking about a conceptual idea
of whether of what gives it significance. You'll see this as we
continue. Let's take a look.
דתנן תנן מטמאין לחים ואין מטמאין יבשים. Detnan, tnan, metamin lachim ve’ein
metamin yeveshim. Our משנה Mishna says only moist, not dried out. אמר
רבי זירא לא קשיא הא בכולן הא במקצתן. Amar Rabbi Zeira lo
kashya, ha bekullan ha bemiktzasan. And this all really also reinforces my
point. It's about as if you have the whole thing or a
part of a thing. If you only have a part of a
rodent and you have enough of a size to cause טומאה, Tumah,
which is כעדשה k’adasha the size of a bean, then if a
part of it and it's dried out, then it no longer causes
טומאה. Tumah. But if you have the entire rodent and it's dried
out and it has its shape, it causes טומאה. Tumah. Now what
difference does that make? Right? Once you have the minimum size, who
cares if you have a little piece of it or the whole
thing? So again, the thing seems to be whether it has significance.
A little piece of a rodent dried out is like insignificant. A
whole rodent, even if it's dried out, if it still retains its
shape, still retains some degree of significance. So that seems to be
the way ריש לקיש Resh Lakish is conceptualizing it, and therefore when
you have those two criteria, the entire one and it is its
shape, it still causes טומאה. Tumah. דתניא Detanya we learned in a
ברייתא, Brayta, אמר רבי יצחק בר רבי ביסני אמר רבי שמעון בר
יוחאי בהם. Amar Rabbi Yitzchak bar Rabbi Bisni amar Rabbi Shimon bar
Yochai bahem.
It says when, when, if you know, if you touch them, what's
the פסוק? pasuk? כל הנוגע בהם, kol hanogea bahem, anybody touches them.
יכול בכולן, yakhol bekullan, maybe you're only טמא tamei if you touch
the entire rodent. תלמוד לומר מהם. talmud lomar mehem. If it says
if it falls from them onto some food, so not the whole
thing. אם מהם, im mehem, from them, יכול במקצתן, yakhol bemiktzasan,
maybe you only need a portion of it, you never need the
whole thing. תלמוד לומר בהם. talmud lomar bahem. But the other verse
says them, the entirety. So what is it? You need the entire
rodent or only a part of it? הא כיצד? ha keitzad? How
do you deal with this? כאן בלח כאן ביבש. kan belach kan
beyavesh. It depends if it's moist or if it's dried. If it's
moist even a small part as long as it's a minimum size.
If it's dried out, it only causes טומאה Tumah if it's the
entirety.
Or you say it's like a limb, you know, that can represent.
There are other times where we also would say that too, that
right, that the whole thing even smaller than the minimum size, but
here we're using it for this purpose. אמר
רבא הני זבוגי דמחוזא, Amar Rava hanei zivugei demachuza, these זבוגים zivugim
of מחוזא. Machuza. מחוזא Machuza is where רבא Rava lived in בבל,
Bavel, and זבוגים zivugim were some type of a rodent. כשלדן קיימת
טמאים. kishildan kayemet tme’im. If their shape is around, presumably these were
things that were often I don't know, you know, like in New
York you might say dead cockroaches or something, you know, things that
maybe they were very common that they were lying around and dried
out, and I mean, and he's saying you know what, these are
the שרצים sheratzim of the תורה, Torah, one of, it's one of
the categories of the שרץ sheretz of the תורה, Torah, and as
long as the shape is still there even after it's dried out,
it still causes טומאה. Tumah. So he just basically took what we
said and just applied it to a real case example. ואמר ריש
לקיש, ve’amar Resh Lakish, ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says basically we're going
to say the same thing now except instead of dried out, but
even a more shocking application about burnt. שרץ שנשרף, sheretz shenisraf, if
the rodent was
burnt, ושלדן קיימת טמאים, veshildon kayemet tme’im, it is טמא. tamei. Now
again, there's two stages of burnt, one is burnt and turned into
ashes, the other is burnt in the sense of like charred, right?
I assume we're talking about charred. Burnt and turned into ashes, at
a certain stage הלכתית halakhically you say it's completely lost its identity,
it's a different thing. Okay?
What? Well, no, you could have the shape, you could have ashes
that still retains its shape, right? Like charcoal.
Like
charcoal, right, exactly. But I assume we're talking much more about charred.
מיתיבי, Meitvei, I'll ask you on this. נמצא שרץ שרוף על גבי
הזיתים, nimtza sheretz saruf algabei hazeisim, if you found, this is a
משנה mishna in טהרות, Taharos, a burnt rodent on top of olives,
right, and the olives were let's say תרומה truma or whatever they
were, they, but you, you wanted to make sure they were טהור,
tahor, and now this was a burnt rodent on top of it.
וכן מטלית המהוה, vekhen matlis hamuha, or you found let's say a
worn out garment, some type of a completely you know tattered garment,
which had been טמא, tamei, but now it's at a stage that
it is so used and tattered that it loses its identity and
it's no longer considered a garment and it no longer causes טומאה.
Tumah. So טהורים, tehorim, the, the olives are טהור. tahor. Meaning you
have, you don't know, when did this garment fall on the olives?
When did this rodent fall on the olives? Did it fall when
it was in a good shape and then got you know worn
out or got burnt later, or did it fall out when it
was already burnt and worn out? So the principle here is, a
principle we've seen before, which is כל הטמאים כשעת מציאתן, kol hatme’im
kesha’at metzi’atan, that you basically assume things are the way you found
them. Although obviously that's not always true, but that's a general rule
that we go by, you know, in order to deal with cases
of doubt. So since you found it and it was already burnt
and you found this garment and it was already worn out, you
can assume that's the way it fell on the olives, and the
olives are
all things are based on the way they're found. אמר רב זירא
Amar Rav Zeira לא קשיא lo kashya הא בכולה הא במקצתה ha
b’kulah ha b’miktzata same thing we said before, do you have an
entire rodent or only a part of it? Of course the problem
is that that משנה Mishnah said שרץ sheretz which would sound like
it was an entire one, but nevertheless that’s the answer. That if
it was, let's just
finish up the
דף Daf דתניא אמר רבי יצחק ברבי ביסנא משום שמיא dtanya amar
Rabi Yitzchak b’rabbi Bisna mishum she’miyo’chai בהם יכול בכולן b’hem yachol b’kulan
תלמוד לומר מהם talmud lomar me’hem מהם יכול במקצתה me’hem yachol b’miktzata
תלמוד לומר בהם talmud lomar b’hem הכיצד haycheitzad כאן בסרוף כאן בשאינו
סרוף. kan b’saruf kan b’she’eino saruf. The same thing we said before
about dry we’re saying here about burnt. Now again if it’s really
completely burnt it’s hard to imagine that it ever causes טומאה tumah
but if it’s charred you can understand it. And again if what
we’re saying is something dried and charred if you have it in
its entirety with its shape it’s going to cause טומאה tumah but
not with its shape or not with its entirety not. It sounds
like what we’re saying is the issue of being dried or charred
is not that it loses its identity because then how could it
retain it just because you have the entire thing with the shape
if it’s only ashes here if it’s not the thing? But it
seems like it loses its significance and therefore when you have other
things that give it the significance like the entirety of it and
retaining the shape that might be enough to retain its significance even
though it is burnt and dried out.
But what would we say for let's say a dried out limb
or a charred limb? Would we say the same thing as it?
No but you're saying anyway your idea that a limb suffices that's
not by a שרץ sheretz by a שרץ sheretz you need the
entire שרץ sheretz as a substitute for the you know for the
כעדשה. k’adasha. But you know but that point that Michael was alluding
to is again an indication that the idea of entire the entire
שרץ sheretz as opposed to a part of it,
you know we see that difference elsewhere which is another area where
there's a question about significance which is how much of a שרץ
sheretz how much of a rodent causes טומאה tumah and normally the
amount is you need the size of a כעדשה k’adasha of a
bean. But if you have an entire שרץ sheretz that’s smaller than
that size it also causes טומאה. tumah. So there again the question
is you need a minimum amount to give it significance. That minimum
amount is either a quantitative minimum, the size of a כעדשה k’adasha
or it's qualitative significance in that it's the entirety of the thing.
It's a בריה birya the entire שרץ. sheretz. So here too what
it's saying is that when it's burnt or dried that undermines its
significance but again if it retains its shape and it's the entirety
it still holds on to it even in those circumstances.
And isn't this what we said by נבילה nevelah or מת? meit?
What? Isn't this by נבילה nevelah and מת? meit?
No by נבילה nevelah we don't say in a whole limb. It's
only by a מת. meit.
Only by a מת. meit. Yeah. From what I remember.
There is some areas about בריה birya which
is other by איסורים issurim like if we would say like a
גיד הנשה gid hanasheh but but generally you're correct. מטמאים לחים metamin
lachim Okay so now we get to the point that everything other
than the נידה niddah blood and the flesh of a corpse is
only when it is fresh not when it is dried out. So
how do you know this? זב דכתיב zav dichtiv by the זב
zav it says רר בשרו rar besaro his it flows in his
flesh. So flow meaning it's liquid. כחלב ורוקו kecholev ve’roko How do
you know about his phlegm and his spit? That it's only when
it's liquid form?
דכתיב כי ירוק dichtiv ki yarok when he spits הזב hazav כעין
רוק ke’eyn rok it has to be in the shape of spit.
It has to be in the so it has to be liquid.
שרץ sheretz rodent. במותם אמר רחמנא bemotam amar rachmana it says that
you touch them in their death. כעין מיתה ke’eyn mita they have
to be like they are when they die. They have to be
still relatively fresh. It's funny you would not have thought מיתה mita
was an
example of being fresh but at the moment of death.
Okay. שכבת זרע shichvat zera How about semen? How do we know
that that still only when it's moist and not when it dries
out? הראויה להזריע hara’uya lehazria because it says שכבת זרע shichvat zera
means that it could cause it could cause conception. So it assumes
that if it's dried out it cannot. I don't know is that
true? If you actually take semen that has dried, is it the
is the sperm in it dead? If you were to if you
were to put it together with an egg would it not could
you not do artificial insemination once it's dried out? I have no
idea. That's what? Don't think it can live indefinitely. No, right. But
in the but I guess after a certain is there a point
where it could dry out and the sperm still be alive? That's
what I'm asking. Does insemination what do you think Rachel? I think
that if it's dry it's probably not good, but I'm just wondering
from this about some the they're making a distinction between semen and
sperm, aren't they? Well the גמרא Gemara didn't know about sperm. I
know but we do, so does that mean that if somebody was
infertile they're...
Right, that's a quite interesting question. The גמרא Gemara never assumes that.
You're right. I mean you know again it gets to the question
about which qualities you're focusing on. When it says ראויה להזריע ra’uya
lehazria it sort of means and
it's now suitable for
fertilization as
they may not
have sperm.
But it's not ראוי להזריע. raui lehazria. First of all, there's a
question about who do we know who's, you know, how determining who
do we think is who's the cause of not being vasectomized.
Right, right, right, right.
Yeah, yeah, I, you know, so there is a גמרא, Gemara, there
were גמרות Gemaras before that did speak about even about sort of
the way the semen comes out and does it come out in
a, you know, in a powerful stream or not, and assuming that
that would be an indicator of whether it was fit to cause
conception or not. So the גמרא Gemara at one stage actually did
think that it might be possible that yes, person by person, maybe
if we could sort of see physically that we assess it as
not fit for doing it, but it never gets to that point
of like medically testing it. Right.
Right, right,
right.
And yet the question is right and it gets to your point
before about how do you define these criteria of ראוי להזריע? raui
lehazria? Does ראוי להזריע raui lehazria literally mean all the qualities that
make it ראוי להזריע? raui lehazria? For example, תוספות Tosafot says the
גמרא Gemara at least believes that something that sperm doesn't cause a
conception unless it's coming out in a powerful stream, so if it's
sitting there, it's not ראוי להזריע. raui lehazria. So תוספות Tosafot says
okay, we're not talking about the you know sort of its way
of being propelled, we're talking about the quality of the thing itself.
So here too you could say, you know, we're talking about just
its physical state, not its presence of the quantity of sperm. It's
always a question about which aspects are you going to use in
your definition. Well, they're right. The question is how literal is the
גמרא Gemara in terms of it having to be ראוי להזריע raui
lehazria in all respects?
I mean if it was in an in vitro, you wouldn't need
a powerful stream. So it's probably true otherwise is because it has
to arrive at...
Right, correct. But תוספות Tosafot points out that even if it's sitting
there and right now can't, so yes,
you are correct, you don't need ראוי להזריע raui lehazria in all
respects. And which ones do you feel are the relevant ones gets
back to the point you made before, that that's really a question
about formalizing and interpreting. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this:
נבילה דכתיב, neveilah dechtiv, and by נבילה neveilah how do we know
it has to be fresh? Because it says כי ימות, ki yamut,
when an animal dies, and again ironically we're saying it means כמתה,
k'mitah, it means fresh, it means just as the moment it died.
Okay. Fresh roadkill.
Fresh, right, exactly, fresh roadkill.
אם יכול להשרות, im yachol lehashrot, now,
if you can put any of these things back into water, lukewarm
water for 24 hours and they will become refreshed, then they are
not considered dried out. בעי רמי בר חמא: ba'ei Rami bar Chama:
לשרותן בפושרן, lishrotan befoshrin,
does the water have to be lukewarm from the entire 24 hour
period? או דילמא תחילתו אף על פי שאין סופו, o dilma techilato
af al pi she'ein sofo, or maybe even if it's not lukewarm
the entire period and it becomes cool after a while, assuming
you're in a cold clime. And the assumption is that if it
has to be lukewarm, then it'll it's more likely that it'll reconstitute
or whatever refresh if you retain it as being lukewarm the entire
period. So תא שמע, ta shema, come in here, תניא: tanya: כמה
היא שהייתן בפושרן, kama hi shehiyatan befoshrin, how long does it have
to remain in lukewarm water? יהודה בן נקוסא אומר מעת לעת, Yehuda
ben Nekusa omer me'et le'et, 24 hours, תחילתו אף על פי שאין
סופו, techilato af al pi she'ein sofo, as long as the beginning
was lukewarm even if the end was not. ורבי עקיבא אומר צריך
שיהו פושרין מעת לעת, v'Rabbi Akiva omer tzarich sheyehu poshrin me'et le'et,
no it has to remain lukewarm the entire 24 hours. So there
you go, it's a debate of תנאים. Tannaim.
Which reminds me of the opposite of מים שלנו, mayim shelanu, you
know?
Yeah, there you go. רבי יוסי אומר בשר המת, Rebbi Yosi omer
basar hamet, now finally Rebbi Yosi says the meat of a the
flesh of a corpse even if it's dried out, excuse me, only
if it's fresh, not right, no, excuse me, yeah, only if it's
fresh, not in its
not if it is dried out. So that seemed to be arguing
on the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma that said that the flesh of
a corpse even dried out causes טומאה. tumah. So let's see what
the גמרא Gemara says. אמר שמואל: amar Shmuel: טהור מלטמא בכזית, tahor
mil'tamei b'chezayit,
it is true that Rebbi Yosi says when the flesh of a
corpse is dried out, it no longer has the standard טומאה tumah
of flesh of a corpse, which means it causes טומאה tumah in
a כזית, kezayit, that was the position of the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma that even dried out it causes טומאה, tumah, he rejects that.
אבל, aval, but he doesn't say it's completely out of the woods.
מטמא טומאת רקב, mitamei tum'at rekev, you might remember we had a
few weeks ago that there's a special type of a טומאה tumah
which is the actual sort of decomposed flesh of a corpse which
is called רקב. rekev. It's very highly special cases you need that
רקב rekev causes טומאה, tumah, if you might remember it has to
be buried in like naked in a you know in a
marble casket that no other things could be mixed into it. Anyway
under very special circumstances the decomposed flesh causes טומאה, tumah, it's not
a כזית, kezayit, it's a different amount, it's the size of a
some type of a larger container. Okay, so that at least it
would have. תניא נמי הכי: tanya nami hachi: רבי יוסי אומר בשר
המת שיבש ואינו יכול לשרות ולחזור כמו שהיה טהור, Rebbi Yosi omer
basar hamet sheyavesh ve'eino yachol lishrot velachzor kemo shehayah tahor, if the
flesh of a corpse dried and it cannot be you know be
reconstituted it is טהור tahor as opposed to the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma who says it's טמא tamei even dry. But טהור מלטמא בכזית,
tahor mil'tamei b'chezayit, it's טהור tahor in the sense
that it's not a כזית kezayit of it or an olive's worth
of it causes טומאה tumah like normal flesh of a corpse. אבל
מטמא טומאת רקב, aval mitamei tum'at rekev, it does cause טומאה tumah
if as decomposed flesh. Okay, so there you go, that is that
is Rebbi Yosi. Now we are done with the issue about dried
out. That was a little bit of a background for this next
משנה Mishnah because we're circling back towards the issue about a woman
and finding stains on her clothing. So let's
take a look at the משנה. Mishnah. שרץ שנמצא במבוי, Sheretz shenimtza
bamavoy, you found a dead lizard in an alleyway. dead rodent in
your courtyard and you wanted to know, you know, you walked over
that area and you wanted to know, did you step on the
rodent? Are you טמא? tamei? What's your status? So טמא למפרע, tamei
lemafrea, you have to assume that that rodent has been there retroactively
for the עד שיאמר בדקתי את המבוי הזה ולא היה בו שרץ
ad sheyomar badakti et hamavoi hazeh velo hayah bo sharetz
until you can say, I checked this מבוי, mavoi, we did a
whole sweep of the מבוי, mavoi, alright, and and we know that
this was, you know, on three weeks ago and we saw then
that there was no rodent. So fine, if the last time you
checked this for rodents was three weeks ago, you have to assume
for the last three weeks this rodent has been here. או עד
שכיבוד o ad shekibbud
or unless actually I combined the two, either until you checked it
or until you did a sweeping, you
know, if you had alternate side of the מבוי mavoi parking because
you did regular cleaning of it, so until the last time you
cleaned or the last time you checked, you have to assume that
the שרץ sharetz was there. וכן, vechen, now of course that raises
the question, fine, let's assume the שרץ sharetz was there, do I
have to assume that I stepped on it, that I walked over
it? Okay, maybe that gets other questions, ספק טומאה ברשות הרבים, רשות
היחיד, safek tumah birshut harabbim, rishut hayachid,
but at least, however you figure that out, at least you have
to start with the assumption the שרץ sharetz was there until the
last time you checked. וכן כתם שנמצא בחלוק vechen ketem shenimtza bechaluk
and now we're getting back to our case, a stain found on
a woman's clothes and she doesn't know, she, you know, she has
to assume it's from her body because it'll be a case where
she can't attribute it elsewhere, we're about to have a whole פרק
perek discussing about the possibility of attributing it elsewhere, but let's say
she can't attribute it elsewhere, she has to assume it came from
her and that she's טמאה. tmeiah. Fine, but when? Starting when? So
מטמא למפרע עד שיאמר בדקתי את החלוק הזה ולא היה בו כתם,
metamei lemafrea ad sheyomar badakti et hachaluk hazeh velo hayah bo ketem,
she has to be concerned that it was on her garment from
as far back as to she can say I checked my garment
and it was free of stains. If two weeks ago she checked
it for stains, then for the last two weeks she has to
assume that the stain might be there. או עד שכיבוד o ad
shekibbud or until the last time she did laundry, but any time
after laundry or the last time she checked for stains, she has
to be concerned it might be there. We had this, right? Right,
we had this, yes, this is the משנה mishnah where it originally
appears, it was quoted earlier. ומטמא בין לח בין יבש umetamei bein
lach bein yavesh and
as we've already said before, stains of a of, you know, of
נדה niddah blood causes טומאה tumah whether whether it is moist or
dried. רבי שמעון אומר, Rebbi Shimon omer, היבש מטמא למפרע והלח אינו
מטמא אלא עד שיהא יכול להיות, hayavesh metamei lemafrea vehalach eino metamei
ella ad sheyehei yachol lihyot, I'm sit... not לחזור, lachzor, but להיות
לח. lihyot lach. He says a very reasonable thing. Look, if you
have a dried-out stain or a dried-out rodent, then you don't know
how long it's been around. So it could be around for three
weeks until the last time you checked your מבוי mavoi or you
laundered your clothes. But if you have a fresh rodent or a
fresh stain, then it could at most, it could have only been
there what, two, three days, or however long it could have been
there and it could still be fresh today. So you don't go
further back than the reasonable amount of time that it could still
be fresh. And that's what he says, which makes a lot of
sense. Of course, once you say that, you should have the opposite,
and then you've had this הרי הוא לשיעורין harei hu l'shiurin is,
okay, fine, you'd have to figure it out, but you could also
have the opposite thing. You could say if it's dried out, so
then, right, it could have been more recent. Right, exactly, that's the
other thing, but it could have, you know, it couldn't have happened
just recently. But of course it doesn't really matter if it happened
just recently because even if it happened before, if it's still around,
it's still dried out, it's still טמא. tamei. The only thing is
that the rodent, if it's dried out, wouldn't be טמא tamei like
we learned before, but you know, some מפרשים meforshim say, the רש"ש
Rashash says it's not super dried out. It doesn't mean dried out
to the point of, you know, completely that it's טהור, tahor, it
just means that it's not fresh. Okay, so that's basically the point.
You have to be concerned that it happened in the past until
you know you've done a check in the past. And then you
have the very reasonable position about רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon that says
but if it's fresh, you don't have to go crazy, you know,
then that obviously puts much much more limits on it. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this, איבעיא להו, ibaia lehu, they raised
the question, עד שכיבוד חזקתו בדוק, ad shekibbud chazkato baduk, why does
until the last time you swept the מבוי, mavoi, why is that
your terminal point? Is it because we say that when you sweep
your מבוי, mavoi, חזקתו בדוק chazkato baduk או דילמא חזקתו מתכבד? o
dilma chazkato mitkabed? Do we say that when you are checking it,
when you are sweeping, you are also checking, or do we say
that the act of sweeping constitutes a checking? Meaning, what do we
say, why are we going back to the last time you you
you swept? Do we say because when you're sweeping, you're also looking
around? Or do we say even if you're not looking around, you're
sweeping would have naturally gotten rid of it? So what's the difference?
ומה נפקא מינה, umai nafk'a minah, exactly, ומה נפקא מינה, umai nafk'a
minah, what difference does it make? דאמר כיבדתי ולא בדקתי. deamar kibbadti
velo badakti. You said, look, I swept, but I wasn't looking. I
told you, I'm honest, I wasn't looking when I was sweeping. I
did a good job sweeping, but I wasn't looking. אי אמרת חזקתו
בדוק, ei amart chazkato baduk, if you say it's only because we
assume you checked as you were sweeping, הלו לא בדק, halo lo
badak, you didn't check. אי אמרת חזקתו מתכבד, ei amart chazkato mitkabed,
no, it automatically gets gets, sort of, you know, swept away in
your act, הא מתכבד, ha mitkabed, so it got swept. swept it
away. The very sweeping swept it away. So that's one נפקא מינא.
nafka mina. אי נמי, ee nami, it says top of נו עמוד
ב, nun vav amud bet, another נפקא מינא nafka mina is דאשתכח
בגומא, de'ishtakach beguma, it was found buried in a hole. אי אמרת
חזקתו בדוק, ee amarta chazkato baduk, if you say that when you
were sweeping you were checking, so מאן דבדוק בגומא נמי בדוק, man
de'baduk beguma nami baduk, if you're checking, you'll check the hole, so
you'll do a good job. אי אמרת חזקתו מתכבד, ee amarta chazkato
mitkabed, if you just say it naturally gets swept away, גומא לא
מתכבד, guma lo mitkabed, it won't get swept out of the hole.
Like you sweep on the surface, you don't necessarily sweep into the
tiny little crevices, so you can't assume that the sweeping got it
out of the hole, but if you checked, you know that it
wasn't in the hole, you would have checked even the holes. וכן
הכתם, veken haketem, now we're not done with our question, we've actually
integrated into the question. And same issue about the stain on the
woman's clothes. איבעיא להו, ibaia lehu, עד שעת כיבוס, ad sh'at kibus,
why do you go back to the time of laundering? דהיי חזקתו
בדוק, de'hai chazkato baduk, that when you launder your clothes first you,
you know, look them over for stains before you launder them and
then if you find the stain presumably you'll get it out. או
דילמא חזקתו מתכבס, o dilma chazkato mitkabes, or do we say that
no, by doing the laundering even without having checked it'll naturally come
out? So the גמרא gemara says למאי נפקא מינא, lemai nafka mina,
again what difference does it make? Same point. דאמר כיבסתי ולא בדקתי,
de'amar kibasti velo badakti, I tell you I laundered it but I
didn't bother checking. אי אמרת חזקתו בדוק, ee amarta chazkato baduk, if
the only reason is that you assume that it, you know, it
wasn't there after the laundering was because you assume I identified it
and therefore got rid of it, so הלא לא בדקתי, halo lo
badakti, in this case I didn't identify it and maybe it's still
around. אי אמרת חזקתו מתכבס, ee amarta chazkato mitkabes, but if you
say even without identifying it, it automatically takes care of itself because
by being laundered it will itself get off of the garment, so
המיתכבס, hamitkabes, it got off of the garment, so I don't need
to also check it. So that's a case where just relying on
the laundering is better, because if you can just rely that the
laundering or the sweeping will do it, even if the guy says
I didn't bother checking as well, I don't need you to check
as well, I just say the laundering or the sweeping will take
care of it. So that's easier in that regard. But the other
case is אי נמי דאשתכח בסטרא, ee nami de'ishtakach besitra, but let's
say it's found in a fold, like being found in a crevice.
אי אמרת חזקתו בדוק, ee amarta chazkato baduk, if you say that
it's good because I assume you'll be checking, so מאן דבדוק בסטרא
נמי בדוק, man de'baduk besitra nami baduk, I assume you check the
folds and even if it's in a fold I assume it came
later because I assume that you checked it at the time and
if it was in the fold you would have gotten rid of
it. אי אמרת חזקתו מתכבס, ee amarta chazkato mitkabes, but if you
rely just on the laundering itself and not on the checking, בסטרא
לא מתכבס, besitra lo mitkabes, it won't get done even if it
is, it won't get done automatically by being in the fold. So
מאי, mai, what do you say? So this reminds me of a
story I once read that somebody was telling her daughter about how
she got her, about a trick to get her kids to do
a, to do like good cleaning in the house which was like,
she says you know what you should do is like you should
like hide like dollar bills or coins or whatever in various places
in the house so then you know when they're cleaning they'll find
it and then they'll get to keep it, you know, you tell
them they can keep what they find. So she says, she says
oh that's a great idea, she says why did you never do
that with us? She said I did. So anyway, so that's the
question about how well, how good of a job you find things
naturally as you're cleaning. Anyway, so the גמרא gemara says like this,
so מאי, mai, so what do we say? So do we assume
that the sweeping and the laundering will take care of it automatically
and then you don't have to intentionally be looking? Or do we
assume you are checking which also helps for cases which we can't
assume the sweeping will take care of like or the laundering like
it's in a crevice. So the גמרא gemara says מאי, mai, what's
the story? So תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear. דתניא אמר
רבי מאיר, de'tanya amar Rabbi Meir, as we've learned, Rabbi Meir says,
מפני מה אמרו השרץ שנמצא במבוי מטמא למפרע עד שיאמר בדקתי את
המבוי הזה ולא היה בו שרץ, mipnei mah amru hasheretz shenimtza bamavoi
metame lemafrea ad sheyomar badakti et hamavoi hazeh velo hayah bo sheretz,
why do we say that if you find a rodent in a
מבוי, mavoi, you say it's טמא tamei all the way back until
you say you've done a check? או עד שעת כיבוד, o ad
sh'at kibud, or until the time that you've swept? מפני שחזקת בני
ישראל בודקין מבואותיהן בשעת כיבודן, mipnei shechazkat bnei Yisrael bodkin mavo'oteihen bish'at
kibudan, because we can trust Jews that when they are sweeping their
courtyards they are checking them as well. So he's very clear. He
doesn't say because the sweeping takes care of it, he says because
they're checking as they are sweeping. ואם לא בדקו הפסידו למפרע, ve'im
lo badku hifsidu lemafrea, and if they tell you that we didn't
check when we swept, we swept but we didn't check, then you've,
then you've lost all the way backwards, then you can't use that
as a terminal point and you have to be concerned even prior
to the sweeping if they admit that they did not check. So
you see it is very clear, it is not according to רבי
מאיר, Rabbi Meir, it is not the sweeping in itself, it is
the checking that is done at the time of the sweeping. ומפני
מה אמרו כתם שנמצא בחלוק מטמא למפרע עד שיאמר בדקתי את החלוק
ולא היה בו כתם, umipnei mah amru ketem shenimtza bechaluk metame lemafrea
ad sheyomar badakti et hachaluk velo hayah bo ketem, why do we
say a stain on a garment is טמא tamei all the way
back until the point that you can say you checked the garment
and there was no stain? או עד שעת כיבוס, o ad sh'at
kibus, or until the time of laundering? So the first is obvious,
but why does laundering help? So he says מפני שחזקת בנות ישראל
בודקות חלוקיהן בשעת כיבוסיהן, mipnei shechazkat bnot Yisrael bodkot chalukeihen bish'at kibusieihen,
because Jewish women check their garments when they are laundering. It is
not just the act of sweeping, the act of laundering, it is
the checking that takes place at that time. So that's his, that's
what רב מאיר Rebbi Meir says, for him it is only because
there is active checking going on. Let's say the husband did the
laundry, is he בודק, boddek, is he not checking? What? Let's say
the husband did the laundry. Yeah, I don't know. רב אחא אמר,
Rav Acha amar, so now רב אחא Rav Acha says, now, this
is a pretty strict, this is a pretty strict position, right? Because
this says if you actually say you didn't check, you're stuck and
you have to go all the way back to forever, for who
knows how long. So now the גמרא Gemara comes with some statements
to somewhat limit it. רב אחא אמר תחזור ותכבסנו. Rav Acha amar
tachzor v'tis-chabsenu. Here, I can tell you a trick to see even
if you didn't check, to determine whether it's an old stain or
a new stain. Go ahead and launder it again. אם נדחה מראיתו,
im nidchah marito, if the stain now is paler than it was
before, then בידוע שלאחר כיבוס, b'yadu'a she-le'achar kibus, then you know it's
a fresh stain. It came after having been laundered because the first
time it's laundered it'll obviously fade. ואם לאו, v'im lav, if it
didn't fade any more than it was when the first time you
saw it, בידוע שלפני כיבוס, b'yadu'a she-lifnei kibus, then you know it's
already been laundered once. So that's a pretty reasonable test, right? So
you have this stain, it's dried, it's faded, is it, I mean
you know when you get certain clothes back from the dry cleaners
or the laundries, you can look at the stain and say oh
my god, like it's clearly been laundered and the stain is still
there so you know it's never coming out. So anyway, he says,
if you've got a stain that it has that faded laundered look,
and you can test by laundering it again and see if it
changes, then you know it was from before the laundry, and therefore
it's not a problem. If afterwards, then it's fresh. Now of course
a question here is, okay, it was from before the laundry and
it was already laundered, but it still was stained and it's still
dried out, so why doesn't it cause טומאה? tumah? Right? But נידה
niddah blood even dried out causes טומאה, tumah, right, presumably. So תוספות
Tosafot says we have to assume that if you're checking the stains
at the time, that you're also putting the garment into the מקווה,
mikvah, and maybe, but of course, does that really help? I mean
that gets the garment טהור, tahor, but what about the fact the
stain is still on it? So I think you do have to
say the assumption here is along the lines of what Rachel said,
which is not just dried out, but at a certain point it's
just a stain. It's not even like the thing that's on the
surface that has some substance to it, but it's dried out, it's
just staining the garment, and then it no longer constitutes actual the
blood itself. Of course, if that were so, anyway, there are some
questions here about why some of this really matters because let's say,
if it's really the fact that it's a stain itself and it
doesn't cause טומאה tumah as a stain, if it doesn't have anything
on the surface of it, so who cares if it's from before
or after the laundry? If once it's a stain it no longer
causes טומאה, tumah, it'd be laundered and be moistened. I don't know.
Anyway, what's not so clear here is, I leave you to think
about, is why does that actually, why does it really matter before
or after the laundry, fresh or not fresh, if it's still a
stain why isn't it causing טומאה? tumah? And if it doesn't cause
טומאה tumah once it's at the stain stage, so who cares if
it's a fresh stain? So anyway. I have a question. Yes. I
guess I don't really understand fundamentally the distinction between a biologic fluid
that is inside and outside your body. I mean, if we're so
concerned that all of these fluids are sources of טומאה, tumah, then
the vessel that carries them, the body, the person, doesn't have a
chance, because there's no, you know, these are the... Right. So it's
a good point. The גמרא's Gemara general principle is that טומאה בלועה,
tumah belu'ah, when it's absorbed in the body, it's not considered halachic
purposes like it exists yet or not. The only exception, which makes
the laws of נידה niddah so challenging, is that when the נידה
niddah blood passes from the uterus through the cervix, then even before
it comes out of the body, the woman is a נידה. niddah.
So that's why all of those internal checks and that's why the
laws of נידה niddah are so challenging. But as a general rule
things that are still in the body are not yet a source
of טומאה. tumah. But in the case of נידה, niddah, that lasts
for a few days. Right. So a woman, I mean just the
idea of a woman doing laundry while a נידה, niddah, it just
seems like one of those things. Right. How do you get out
of a world of טומאה וטהרה? tumah v'taharah? Yeah, it's pretty impossible
if you consider between the fact that the man, when they're having
sex, then the man is a בעל קרי, ba'al keri, when they're
not, he has a seminal emission so he's טמא tamei for a
day, when they're not having sex and the woman's a נידה, niddah,
and then you have all the things that a child does, whatever,
I mean you have טומאה, tumah, I think you have to assume
that טומאה tumah is the norm, not the exception. And unless you're
dealing with תרומה terumah or you're really going to extreme efforts to
eat your חולין בטהרה, chullin b'taharah, then טומאה tumah is completely the
norm of life. So, but you're right, it is extremely difficult to
avoid. So then why do we care if we find... Right, so
that's a good point, meaning the way when you read... these משניות
mishnayot it makes it sound like טהרה tahara is the norm and
that these are right, and you're right, it's hard to imagine exactly
how you could live your a normal life without always having a
heightened concern about the טומאה tuma issue unless unless you're a כהן
kohen and then it is a little bit extreme and very challenging.
True. I think the concern is that you would get kind of
like a mentality that natural things are right, well right, okay, it's
true, you develop a kind of hyper alertness when it's clear that
you don't have a chance because there's no real way out of
any of this. Right, right. Yeah, I see. I mean, you know
again, it's more all more true by a כהן, kohen, other but
it is true, it's and the fact that the whole beginning of
the מסכת masechet was about women checking two times a day every
single day whether they're נדות niddot or not נדות niddot or whatever
the entire month, you know, we can't even I think begin to
understand that type of, you know, that hyper whatever obsessive mentality or
how people could live through that. It could just be this whole
idea theoretically, theoretically everybody would be so perfect, but this is how
you should really act. Yeah, I mean, that could be as well.
There's always that question, right, there's always that question about how much
when our חז״ל Chazal describing the actual lived reality or more about
a theoretical reality, that is a question. Yeah. How do you distinguish?
So with this, with this garment that has a כתם ketem on
it, so so what's becoming טמא? tamei? The garment itself and somebody
who touches it and the woman wearing it presumably. Well, and it's
just you have to assume she became a נדה. niddah. So you
are correct in terms of so Michael is actually correct and that
helps somewhat that the issue about that I raised about who cares
if the stain was before or after, it's still right now visible
and it's still a stain. Michael says, yeah, but the question is
when, how far back the woman has to assume that she was
טמאה tmeia and you are correct, that at least is a profound
difference. So somehow if the stain's been been laundered, you can assume
that it's, you know, if it's clear it's been laundered, you assume
that this stain is old, if not, you assume it's fresh. Certainly
one נפקא מינה nafka mina is how far back this woman has
to be concerned that she actually, you know, that she was a
נדה. niddah. What's the status of the stain itself? Does laundering get
it out of its status of being a כתם? ketem? That's not
so clear. But you are definitely correct in terms of her status.
Yes. I just wanted, so we have to, yes, go ahead. I
just wanted to bring, so you might consider the aspect of not
applying our framework to right, it's hard to understand their their mindset
in terms of this, it this may have significance in terms of
their being close to השם, Hashem, right, so so then it might
not be a crazy thing to us. Sure, their whole, exactly. Look,
and there are plenty of people that upset about a million other
details nowadays in הלכה halacha because we don't have the טומאה וטהרה
tuma v'tahara to upset us about, so all right, anyway, so let's
take a look where the גמרא Gemara says. The problem, the problem
is that we learned this today. And very few people learn it
other than those doing the דף היומי. daf yomi. The problem is
that the the attitudes that get transmitted through this create a lot
of the problems that presumably orthodoxy represents and really what she says
is it's not only the way women are viewed as complete objects
that can only result in a problem, but I mean, I I
can't help but connect this to the very disturbing idea of children
as sexual objects because they don't have any of these emissions so
they would be very attractive from the perspective of טומאה וטהרה tuma
v'tahara and I think that seems to be a little bit of
a jump, but I think that's a jump, but I do agree
that there's a heightened concern about all of these details which. Not
in a mentality that values keeping oneself pure. Right, all right, let's
let's leave it at that. But I do hear certainly the heightened,
you know, detailed pervasive, you know, issues is is true throughout הלכה
halacha and particularly in a world of טומאה וטהרה. tuma v'tahara. So
let's see anyway where the גמרא Gemara goes with this. רב אחא
אמר תכסנו ותכבסנו. Rav Acha amar tichasnu v'techabasnu. Here's what you do.
Do another laundering, do a test. אם נתמרטו, Im nitmarto, if it
fades again or if it fades, בידוע שלאחר כיבוס, beyaduah shele'acher kibus,
it's fresh and therefore you know that you only have to worry
until the point of laundering because you can see that this is
a post laundering and you only worry back to the time of
laundering. ואם לאו, V'im lav, if it doesn't fade again, בידוע שלפני
הכיבוס, beyaduah shelifnei hakibus, you know it's from before the כיבוס kibus
and therefore even better and therefore you're completely presumably well well I
don't know even better even worse I guess then you have to
assume that it's been around since from forever and you don't know
when's the last time it happened was. Right. רבי אומר אינו דומה
כתם שלאחר הכיבוס לכתם שלפני הכיבוס. Rebbi omer eino domeh ketem shele'acher
hakibus l'ketem shelifnei hakibus. You don't even need to re-launder it, you
can just look at it. One after laundering is not the same
as before. שזה מקדיר וזה מגליד. shezeh makdir v'zeh maglid. One of
them sort of like pierces in, one of them is completely. inside
the garment and just is a stain, the other has actually a
type of a crust meaning has some surface stuff to it. So
שמע מינה, shema mina, the גמרא Gemara says חזקתו בדוק שמע מינה.
chezkaso baduk shema mina. So you see on the one hand the
reason that the laundering helps is because you assume you actually actively
do a check. Once that's true we have to worry about what
if you didn't actively do a check and you have other ways
of trying to test by either inspecting it or relaundering it to
determine whether this is fresh or not fresh. Okay, if it's not
fresh on the one hand that means that the woman herself she
doesn't know how far back she's טמא tamei because this came even
from before the time of laundering. You can see it's an old
stain who knows when she actually saw it and when she's טמא
tamei maybe weeks and weeks and weeks ago. On the other hand
whether the stain itself remains to be טמא, tamei, that is not
clear but the Michael is correct, the big difference is how far
back he has to be concerned. And since you can see that
it's fresh it limits the amount of time. Okay, ומטמי בין לח
בין יבש u-metammei bein lach bein yavesh and this is causes טומאה
tumah whether fresh or dry, something we pretty much already said. אמר
רבי אלעזר לא שנו אלא שרץ אבל כתם לח נמי מטמא למפרע.
Amar Rabbi Elazar lo shanu ela sheretz aval kesem lach nami metammei
le-mafrea. אימא מיבש הוה ומיא נפל עליה. Eima mi-yavesh havah ve-maya nafal
aleih. This statement of Reb Yose that if it's fresh you only
have to worry for the last few days, that's only about a
rodent. But if you have a fresh drop of blood, a moist
drop of blood, you can't say oh I only have to worry
the last few days. Why? Maybe it was dried and a little
water fell on it and now it looks fresh but it's not
really fresh. So the גמרא Gemara says שרץ נמי אימא יבש הוה
ומיא נפל עליה? Sheretz nami eima yavesh havah ve-maya nafal aleih? How
about a rodent? Why don't we say it got dried and a
little water fell on it and it just looks fresh? So no,
אי איתא דהכי הוא, Ei issa de-hachi hu, if that was the
case, אימטויי אימטוט, imtu-ei imtut, it would have sort of like it
would have sort of like you know it would have not dissolve
but like crumbled or whatever if it you know would not have
retained it wouldn't look the same if it dried up and water
fell on it and therefore by a rodent if it looks fresh
you know it's fresh, it limits the time you're concerned, blood if
it looks fresh might not really be fresh and cannot does not
limit the time you are concerned. Let's take a look now at
the next משנה mishna and now we're turning to the focus which
is going to really dominate for the next good while which is
this issue about finding stains. So the first one is the question
about how far back do you have to be concerned that the
stain might have been up to the laundry or as we discussed
maybe even prior to the laundry but certainly all the way back
to the last time of laundering. Let's look at the משנה. mishna.
כל הכתמים הבאים מרקם טהורים. Kol ha-kesamim ha-baim mi-Rekem tehorim. All stains
that come from רקם, Rekem, a certain city in Israel, are טהור.
tahor. רבי יהודה מטמא. Rebbi Yehuda metammei. Reb Yehuda we will I
will tell you Reb Yehuda says they're טמא tamei מפני שהן גרים
וטועים mipnei she-hen gerim ve-toim because they are converts but they err.
So what does this mean? It means that there's two assumptions. Number
one is that the stains of non-Jews are not טמא, tamei, only
stains of Jews, because the Torah law of נדה niddah even though
there's rabbinic laws that applies to non-Jews it doesn't apply to their
stains. And the other general assumption tends to be that Jews don't
normally are normally careful, Jewish women about their stained garments because they're
a source of טומאה tumah and they don't let them just sort
of laying around. So here the first statement is that all these
stains are טהור. tahor. Why? Because basically we can assume they come
from non-Jews. The Jews that live in the town are going to
be careful with their stains. The stains that are going to be
that you're going to find are going to come from the non-Jews
and therefore they're טהור. tahor. And Reb Yehuda says no, they're טמא
tamei because actually the people you think are the non-Jews are actually
converts and they're making a mistake either they're thinking they're not Jews
or that they are not careful with their stains or even but
whatever it is there are people in the town that are Jews
and are not careful with their stains, converts who make mistakes and
therefore we do have to be concerned about it. הבאי מבין עובדי
כוכבים טהורים. ha-bai mi-bein ovdei chochavim tehorim. Now this is the general
rule: if it comes from among non-Jews it's טהור. tahor. ובין ישראל
ובין הכותים u-bein Yisrael u-bein ha-Kutim if it comes from Jews and
from Samaritans רבי מאיר מטמא. Rebbi Meir metammei. Reb Meir says they're
טמא, tamei, obviously they're stains from Jews. וחכמים מטהרים ve-Chachamim metaherin and
חכמים Chachamim say it's טהור tahor מפני שלא נחשדו על כתמיהן, mipnei
she-lo nechshedu al kesmeihen, they are not irresponsible with their stains. So
basically of course okay so where did these stains come from? So
let's take a look what the גמרא Gemara says. קפסיק ותני. Kapsik
ve-sani. First it's going to focus on the word רקם, Rekem, on
where the things are coming from. אפילו מתרמוד. Afilu mi-Tarmod. It says
that any stains that come from non-Jews are טהור tahor even if
they're coming from תרמוד. Tarmod. Okay. Why is תרמוד? Tarmod? Because תרמוד
Tarmod was a city that the גמרא Gemara was interested in. אמר
רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, זאת אומרת מקבלים גרים מתרמוד. zos omeres
mekablim gerim mi-Tarmod. There's a question about תרמוד Tarmod was a city
that was assumed to be non-Jewish but there were some people that
thought actually that it was a city that was the that was
the descendants of intermarriage of Jews and non-Jews and actually they were
Jewish and that there were a lot of ממזרים mamzerim there because
there were a lot of and therefore the question would be that
if somebody were to convert from תרמוד Tarmod would you have to
be concerned that they were a ממזר mamzer and you could not
allow them to wait why would they be a ממזר mamzer because
that was just the question about no not נדה niddah is not
a not ממזרות mamzerus but there was a question about you know
yeah there was I mean, why would they be more of a
ספק safek than anyone else? I mean, that was the question. There
was clearly an issue about... I don't know, there was just that
question about what that status of that town was. Was that it
was known that basically Jews don't marry into people of that town.
And the question was why? Was it because they were non-Jews or
because there was some assumption there that actually this was the... they
were offsprings of ממזרים? mamzerim? There was a big question mark about
what the status was, but it was generally assumed to be off-limits.
So the question would be, would be if they... the concern was
ממזרים, mamzerim, you could not accept converts because A, you wouldn't need
to convert, but B, converting would entail a ממזר mamzer still couldn't
marry in. If they were just non-Jews and you convert, then fine,
you can marry in. So a ממזר mamzer who wants to convert
you can't convert him. A ממזר mamzer doesn't need to convert. The
point is that conversion won't help. If they're ממזרים, mamzerim, then they
don't need to convert and conversion won't help. And if they're not
ממזרים, mamzerim, then they need to convert and conversion will help. So
what is their status? So Rabbi Yochanan says the fact that we
assume all the cities are okay and we didn't single out תרמוד
Tarmod is a pretty funny inference, tells us that תרמוד Tarmod is
assumed like standard non-Jews, not a special case, and therefore מקבלים גרים
mekabelim gerim and you can accept גרים gerim and marry within. איני?
והא רבי יוחנן וסביא, Eini? V'ha Rabbi Yochanan v'Savya, Rabbi Yochanan סביא,
Savya, interesting name, the elder, דאמרי תרווייהו, d'amri tavaiu, they both say
אין מקבלים גרים מתרמוד. ain mekabelim gerim mitarmod. You cannot accept converts.
We have to assume that
they're ממזרים mamzerim there and therefore you cannot marry into them even
if they convert. וכי תימא, v'chitima, זאת ולא סבירא ליה, zot vlo
svira lei, if he says, well, that's
the assumption of our משנה, mishna, but we don't rule that way?
ואמר רבי יוחנן הלכה כסתם משנה. v'amar Rabbi Yochanan halacha kestam mishna.
We rule like a סתם משנה. stam mishna. So גמרא Gemara says
אמוראי נינהו ואליבא דרבי יוחנן. Amora'ei ninhu v'aliba d'Rabbi Yochanan. Fine, it's
a debate of אמוראים Amoraim how to deal with Rabbi Yochanan, you
know, what Rabbi Yochanan said. Whether this משנה mishna suggests, and again,
the משנה mishna is an innocent משנה, mishna, it just says non-Jews
כתמים ketamim are טהור. tahor. But do we sort of read it
to say, oh, any place we assume is non-Jews, even this place
of תרמוד Tarmod where there's a discussion what their status is, we're
going to treat them as straight non-Jews? Do we read the משנה
mishna that way or not? Or the משנה mishna really isn't even
making a comment about this funny place of תרמוד? Tarmod? Okay, let's
just finish up to the next משנה. mishna. מבני ישראל, mi-bnei Yisrael,
so it says if they come from Jews. רבנן, Rabanan, the rabbis
who say if it comes from Jews it's not a problem. ואי
דדישראל מטהר, v'id d'Yisrael metaher, if stains of Jews are טהור, tahor,
דמאן מטמא? d'man metamei? So whose stains are טמא? tamei? So the
גמרא Gemara says חסורי מיחסרא והכי קתני. chisuri mechsara v'hachi katani. It's
missing some words and here's how it has to be taught. מבני
ישראל טמא, מבני הכותים, mi-bnei Yisrael tamei, mi-bnei hakutim, if it comes
from Jews, you know that the stains are coming from Jews, it's
טמא. tamei. If it's coming from Samaritans, Rabbi Meir מטמא. metamei. Rabbi
Meir says it's a problem, דכותים גרי אמת הן. d'Kutim gerei emet
hein. They are real converts and therefore it is stains from Jews.
וחכמים מטהרים. vachachamim metaherim. The חכמים Chachamim say it's טהור. tahor. דכותים
גרי אריות הן. d'Kutim gerei arayot hein. Their כותים Kutim are not...
are only converted because of the lions. They're not real converts, they're
not real Jews and therefore their stains are טהור. tahor. So גמרא
Gemara says אי הכי, i hachi, if that's the issue, it's an
issue about the status of Samaritans. שלא נחשדו על כתמיהן. she-lo nechshdu
al kitmehen. It shouldn't say because they're not suspect of mishandling their
stains. It should have said the reason it's not a problem is
because of גרי אריות איבעיא ליה gerei arayot niv'la lei because they're
not real Jews. אלא הכי קאמר. ella hachi kamar. Here's how you
have to read the משנה. mishna. מבני ישראל ומבני הכותים טמאים. mi-bnei
Yisrael u-mi-bnei hakutim tameiyim. If it comes, we know it comes from
Jews and from Samaritans, we know it's their stains and it's טמא.
tamei. דכותים גרי אמת הן. d'Kutim gerei emet hein. Even Samaritans are
real converts and they're Jews. So when we know we're dealing with
their stains it's טמא. tamei. But here's our issue. Rabbi Meir... no,
everybody. הנמצאים בערי ישראל. ha-nimtza'im b'arei Yisrael. What if you don't know
where it came? You know, it's not that you know that this
is a Jew's stain. It's just you found it in the middle
of a street, a garment with a stain of it in the
middle of a Jewish city. טהורים. tehorim. You can assume it's טהור
tahor even if it's in a Jewish city. Why? שלא נחשדו על
כתמיהן וצנועי טמני להו. she-lo nechshdu al kitmehen v'tzni'ei matni lehu. Because
they're not... they don't mishandle their stains, they put them away, they
don't want other people to become טמא. tamei. So even if you
find it in a Jewish city, you can assume it came from
the one or two non-Jews from among them, or maybe it wasn't
a נדה niddah stain, maybe it was the stain of some chicken
or something, or some other bloodstain. You don't have to worry because
any stains that will be found in the middle of the street
are not טמא. tamei. People are careful with their stains. Now, הנמצאים
בערי כותים, ha-nimtza'im b'arei Kutim, let's say they're found in Samaritan cities.
Rabbi Meir מטמא. metamei. Rabbi Meir says that is a concern, דנחשדו
על כתמיהן, d'nechshdu al kitmehen, because they're not responsible with their stains,
they're not concerned about those causing טומאה tumah and therefore that is
a concern. וחכמים מטהרים שלא נחשדו על כתמיהן. vachachamim metaherim she-lo nechshdu
al kitmehen. And the rabbis say, no, even the Samaritans are as
careful with their stains as the Jews. So the basic rule is
the following, right, stains of non-Jews is not a problem, stains of
Jews is a problem. But when you find a stain, you have
to be concerned that it might be coming from a Jew who's
not careful. So if it came from a non-Jew it doesn't matter,
if it came from a Jew and if a Jew is careful,
then then it's not a problem. So maybe you could always assume
any stain that you find in the middle of the street is
okay. So the only time we would have to be concerned is
about people that are טמא tamei but are not careful. And that's
why the first משנה mishna spoke about רקם Rekem and the issue
about maybe they're converts and they're not careful with, you know, these
laws. And the end of the משנה mishna spoke about Samaritans. But
a normal case of a Jew... All right, let's back up for
today. Which city or not-Jewish city is not a problem. Not Jews
is not טמא tamei and Jews are careful, so it would not
be a טמא tamei stain. The only concern is special cases where
it's טמא tamei and the people would not be careful and that's
what the point in the משנה. mishnah.